# Joseph Ruiz

Seattle, WA 98116 | 360-970-6033 | ruizjoseph0@gmail.com

Github ruizj3 | medium.com/@ruizj3

# Sr. BI Analyst/Software Engineer

Professional experience in various data analysis projects regarding financial and operational issues. Created powerful BI and Tableau dashboards for quicker macro-decision making and iterated over many machine learning models for anomaly detection. Will continue to use software engineering tools and data analysis experience to create data-driven products that also generate proper and useful data in the backend.

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Powerbi, SQL, Tableau, PRISM, Jaspersoft, Metabase, Python, R, dbt (ETL tool), Ruby, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Java, C#, Excel, Access, SAGE, Clickbase, STATA, Eviews, Oracle(JDEdwards ERP), React.js/Redux, Golang, Drone, Airflow

#### **TECHNICAL PROJECTS**

Pill and Bill - github.com/ruizj3/pill and bill; github.com/ruizj3/pills backend | Demo: https://bit.ly/3cHqXU8 React/Redux frontend and Rails API backend to monitor patient prescriptions

## **EXPERIENCE**

Shipt Seattle, WA Sr. Data Engineer 11/2022 - Present

- Lead development of dbt models transition to Enterprise Warehouse for source of truth accuracy
- Modify app pipelines in Golang to manage shift from AWS to GCS structure
- Develop metric pipelines for single SoT and create tests for accuracy
- Analyze Tableau tech debt for optimization and metric creation and implement changes
- Manage CI/CD changes using Drone for various pipeline and image updates
- Airflow DAG and Snowflake task troubleshooting and updating

Truepill. Inc. Seattle, WA Sr. BI Analyst 02/2022 - 11/2022

- Lead development of dbt models for source of truth accuracy
- Develop base models to compare production data with ERP reporting and analysis
- Automate models to alert stakeholders to forecasted drops in plan or average expectations of revenue and costs
- Develop dashboards allowing for what-if analysis and completely moved the Finance org off of Gsheets/Excel

Convoy, Inc. Seattle, WA **Business Analyst** 07/2021 - 02/2022

- Analyze carrier health related to dedication contracts
- Recommend product changes to increase shipment completion
- Analyze shipper/lane health to increase carrier confidence
- Revamp reporting with whichever tool meets the actual needs of the business users
- Recommend changes to ML models for accurate forecasting of expected volume of shipments

Tango Card, Inc. Seattle, WA 04/2019 - 07/2021

**Business Intelligence Analyst** 

- Develop data definitions w/C-suite assistance across the org
- Define metrics necessary for new product developments
- Study product affects and changes on existing and potential customers
- Manage reporting data pipeline for BI tools for C-level meetings
- ML model creation for fraud analysis reducing false positives freeing up Risk Analysts time
- Utilized dbt(data build tool) to programmatically create sql queries that are auditable and establish data definitions

# TrueBlue. Inc. Financial Analyst, Operational Accounting

Tacoma, WA 01/2017 - 04/2019

- Created DSO root cause analysis reporting to SVP treasury
- Reserve lookback analysis to establish better reserve policies
- Recommendations for identifying concerning customer accounts or branch activities for further review Promoted from: Financial Analyst, Pricing
- National Pricing for major accounts accounting for 30% of U.S. revenue
- Dashboard creation for National Sales directors utilizing PowerBI, Azure, Tableau, R and SQL
- PayRate probability and fill rate management

### **EDUCATION**

**University of Southern California** Master of Science in Financial Engineering **Flatiron School** 

Los Angeles, CA 08/2021 - 05/2023 Seattle, WA Full Stack Web Development, Ruby on Rails and JavaScript program

General Assembly
Data Science (Python) Online program

University of Washington

B.S. Economics

11/ 2019 - 10/2020 Seattle, WA 08/ 2018 - 11/2018 Seattle, WA 08/2013